"Cold Water Immersion for Gout Flares"
For centuries, cold temperatures
have been used by humans
for therapeutic, health,
and sporting recovery purposes.
I had a series of videos
on the sporting recovery case
starting with this one,
and then another
on immune function.
What else might cold be used
for therapeutically?
Cold plunges do not seem
to affect cholesterol
or body weight nor blood
pressures over the long-term.
Neither systolic nor diastolic
blood pressures were altered
in the long-term
by cold water exposure.
After our first plunge,
our blood pressure may go up,
but over time,
our body seems to adapt.
During cold exposure,
our brain doesn't work as well,
but there isn't much evidence
of any residual effect
besides a transient boost
I covered before.
Cold showers may help
with priapism,
which is a prolonged erection
persisting longer
than four hours.
I didn't realize that could turn
into a surgical emergency,
but the prolonged lack
of new oxygenated blood
can cause some of the penile
tissue to die off.
Before it gets to that, you can
try ice packs or cold showers.
In this case, the patient was
instructed to vigorously climb
up and down a set of hospital
stairs for ten minutes,
and within seven,
he successfully deflated.
What about cold water for burns?
Misinformation regarding
first aid for burns
is said to be ubiquitous online.
For example, due to the high
frequency of toothpaste
being applied to burns,
Colgate had to post
something on their website
urging people not to use
toothpaste for burn injuries.
More serious is the suggestion
to immerse a burn in ice water.
Ice or ice water
can make matters worse,
preventing blood flow and
increasing burn depth and pain.
So, what should we do for burns?
A full 20 minutes of cool
running water has been proven
to be the most effective
first aid intervention
in improving burn outcomes,
associated with faster healing,
and decreased odds
of full thickness burns,
hospital admission,
and need for skin grafts.
Twenty minutes
of cool running water.
What about using cold
to treat flares
of a painful inflammatory
arthritis called gout,
caused by crystals of uric acid
forming in our joints,
crystallizing out of our blood
like rock candy.
Since uric acid is more likely
to crystallize
at lower temperature,
maybe that's why people get gout
flares in their toes
or grow crystals in their ears--
the areas of the body
that may be cooler.
So, if cooling of the joints
causes crystal precipitation,
one might be concerned that
applying cold could precipitate
and worsen acute gout attacks.
That may be why some doctors
have suggested applying heat
rather than cold
to affected joints.
You don't know, though,
until you put it to the test,
and indeed, the application
of covered ice packs--
never apply ice
directly to the skin--
for 30 minutes 4 times a day
resulted in a significantly
greater reduction in pain,
compared to the control group.
What about cold water immersion
for gout,
dunking the inflamed joint
for 20 minutes a day for 4 weeks
in water that's more cool
than cold--
like in the 70s Fahrenheit
(21 - 26 °C)?
That led to decreased pain,
stress, anxiety, and depression,
and increased joint mobility,
physical activity,
and quality of life.
Fantastic!
Now, there didn't seem to be
an actual improvement
in inflammation;
the cool water may not
actually be affecting
the course of the disease
but rather,
just causing a kind of numbing
or pain-killing effect,
but, look, either way, what
a cheap, safe, easy treatment
to help alleviate
such a painful condition.
What about cold packs
for myalgia,
which means muscle pain
or muscle aches?
Here, study subjects applied a
cold gel pack for low back pain
for 10 minutes,
and although pain had lessened
at the end of the 10 minutes,
by 30 minutes, no significant
difference was seen.
Isn't 10 minutes
better than nothing?
Well, there is
a cautionary tale
from the anti-inflammatory
drug literature.
Although NSAID drugs
like ibuprofen or naproxen
serve as a common
management strategy
for numerous forms
of musculoskeletal complaints,
evidence suggests that
these drugs may contribute
to tendon degradation
due to less blood flow
because the inflammation
was tamped down.
Inflammation from injury plays
a role in the healing process.
That's what acute inflammation
is for.
Similarly, there are data
indicating an increased risk
for acute pain to transition
to chronic pain
with NSAID use.
In other words,
anti-inflammatory drugs
could cause chronic pain.
Despite pain-killing efficacy
in the short term,
the management
of acute inflammation
may be counterproductive
for long-term outcomes
of low back pain sufferers,
in that it could end up
resulting in more chronic pain
in the long run.
Then what about using heat
therapy for something like
delayed onset muscle soreness,
that soreness you may get
the day after a heavy workout?
A total of 32 randomized
controlled trials involving
more than 1,000 patients
were compiled,
and the heat worked better.
The application of cold therapy
within one hour after exercise
can reduce pain within the
first 24 hours after exercise,
but heat therapy after exercise
can extend that relief
for longer than 24 hours.
A meta-analysis comparing the
effectiveness of nine different
cold and heat modalities
found that for people with this
delayed onset muscle soreness,
hot packs proved
the most effective
for pain relief
over the first 48 hours.